<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dying infants sav'd by grace proved and the blessd man with his blessedness described in a sermon preached near Namptwich in Cheshire at the burial of a deceased infant, July 25, 1695 / by S.A.</title>
            <author>Acton, Samuel, d. 1740?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26309</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28175</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10445601</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10445601</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45045</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26309)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45045)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1392:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dying infants sav'd by grace proved and the blessd man with his blessedness described in a sermon preached near Namptwich in Cheshire at the burial of a deceased infant, July 25, 1695 / by S.A.</title>
                  <author>Acton, Samuel, d. 1740?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author and sold by A. Fabian,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Samuel Acton -- NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant salvation.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45045:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dying Infants.</hi> SAV'D BY GRACE, PROVED: And the <hi>Bleſſed Man</hi> with his <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> Deſcribed. In a SERMON preached near <hi>Namptwich</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> at the Burial of a deceaſed Infant, <hi>July</hi> 25. 1695. By <hi>S. A.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 18.3.</hi>
               </bibl> Verily, I ſay unto you, Except ye be converted, and become as little Children, ye ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Cor. 13.7.</hi>
               </bibl> Charity hopeth all things.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and ſold by <hi>M. Fabian</hi> at <hi>Mercers Chappel</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45045:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45045:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>AMong all things knowable, I think nothing more neceſſary for you to endeavour the ſound knowledg of, than this, That you and yours are, and ſhall be bleſſed: as a means thereunto this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. But,</p>
            <p>What entertainment theſe Lines may meet with in the World, I know not; neither am I over-thoughtful, being reſolved chearfully to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go whatever Cenſures ſhall be my lot to meet with from the differing Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of my Readers. But ſince I have ſatisfaction that my good meaning will be acceptable with many, I ſhall under their favourable acceptance take repoſe and ſhelter from the ſharp and undue reflections of others. For as the moſt ingenious Cook cannot prepare a Diſh to the good liking of all, but ſome or other, from the weakneſs of a vitiated Palat, or ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their affection, will diſguſt the ſame: So 'tis believ'd, the moſt learned Man that ever wrote, could not ſo temper his Matter as to obtain univerſal Approbation, but either the ignorant or prejudiced would quarrel with it. Yet this advantage the Learned have, (if judicious) that their known Learning, and acquired Aptitude, carries an Authority ſufficient to ſtill the Noiſe of the ſimple, and to command the Minds of all, firſt to read, and then to judg: Whereas the Illiterate have not any thing to render their Labours acceptable, but the Goodneſs of their Deſign, and the Bleſſing of God; which I ſincerely wiſh may attend thee in reading theſe Papers in order to thy Bleſſedneſs.</p>
            <p>This Sermon was preached more than three Years ſince, at the Funeral of my Friend's Infant Child, and at his requeſt; and from this Text by the intreaty of another of my Friends; and with deſign to adminiſter comfort to ſome ſorrowful Women, who through the weakneſs of their Faith had long grieved under tormenting Fears, not knowing what the State of their deceaſed Babes is after Death. From hence I took occaſion to diſplay, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my meaſure and time, the Immenſity of Divine Goodneſs, and to free it from thoſe Reſtraints that caſt diſhonour upon it, and are no way co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent with Immenſity. The Arguments, as now preſented, are the ſame I then offered, tho a little inlarged in tranſcribing, with ſome ſmall Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in other parts of the Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>The Salvation of all dying Infants is a Subject innocent in it ſelf, and conſistent with Nature: And were the vileſt of Men free from the Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Divine Laws, they would not (out of their mad fits, and in a ſedate mind) do any thing injurious to their natural Iſſue, but foſter ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45045:3"/>and miniſter all they could to the advantage of their Young. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore believe my ſelf under the advantage of all Mens wiſhing me good luck, from the deſirableneſs of the thing; and if in this undertaking it be not cleared to general ſatisfaction, it ariſes not from any doubtfulneſs of the Matter, but from want of skill in the management of it: and might my inability excite fitter Inſtruments to hit the Mark I have aimed at, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Evidence as undeniable as the Fact is, I ſhould be glad.</p>
            <p>In the mean time let none ſuppoſe that God in his Nature is more cruel and leſs tender of his Offspring, than Man and the maneſt Animal is of theirs; who, as our bleſſed Saviour teacheth, <hi>Matth. 7.11.</hi> from his ſuperabounding Goodneſs, is much more ready to ſhew kindneſs, than the moſt tender Parents on Earth can be. Neither is there any thing in all the Sacred Records that I know of, which looks like an inſtance of Severity in God to the damning of one dying Infant in the World: It there be, 'tis ſurely that of the Infants that periſhed in the flames of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> which <hi>Jude</hi> ſtiles <hi>the Vengeance of Eternal Fire,</hi> v. <hi>7.</hi> Yet I think none will imagine that Fire was Eternal, whereby thoſe wicked Perſons were puniſhed from Heaven, but rather a Figure and Repreſentation of the aſtoniſhing Miſery they muſt ſuffer in the other World, as 'tis often compared to Fire, from the ſharpneſs and violence of it. Neither can any conclude hence, that the Infants which pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in <hi>Sodom</hi> for their Fathers Wickedneſs, ſhall ſo periſh in Hell for ever: <hi>To ſay ſo</hi> (as the Learned
<note n="*" place="margin">In his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> 4.11.</note> Dr. <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi> has it) <hi>would be a harſh term, no way ſutable to the nature and proceedings of God, who is ſo far from puniſhing Children eternally for the Sins of their impious Parents, that ſometimes he ſpares them and their Cities from the flames and ruins of temporal Judgments, for ſake of their innocent Babes, as in the caſe of</hi> Ninive, <hi>Jonah 4.10, 11.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I had contented my ſelf in taking a view of theſe Lines, and therein have pleaſed my ſelf, had it not been for the importunity of Friends (dear to me) to yield them a revival of that pleaſure in reading, which they had in hearing of 'em. And that they, and all into whoſe hands they ſhall come, may have them bleſſed, to their preſent and eternal Happineſs, is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>S. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:45045:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ROM. 4.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſſed is the Man to whom the Lord will not impute Sin.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS Epiſtle, of which our words are a part, was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> the greateſt part of which is ſpent in labouring the deciſion of many conſiderable points of Doctrin, to clear up the Truth of things which lay diſputable among them, and for the ſettling of the Saints there in a ſtedfaſt belief of the truth of things neceſſary to be received and believed by them; one of which Doctrins, if not the moſt conſiderable, is that of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the knowledg of which is neceſſary to our cheriſhing right Sentiments of it in our own Souls, for the yielding us hope and ſtrong Confidence of a ſure and certain ſecurity from Sin and Wrath, being thereby encompaſt with a Wall invincible, not to be ſhaken by the moſt furious Efforts that Men or Devils, the Fleſh or the World can make againſt us.</p>
            <p>In this and the foregoing Chapter, the Apoſtle ſhews by many Arguments, that Man guilty of Sin, and juſtly condemned by the righteous Law of God to death, is juſtified by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt, and by Faith only, as <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. from <hi>verſe</hi> 20, to the end, where the Apoſtle is refuting the Error of every Juſticiary in the World, whether Phariſaical, Papal, or others, who plead for Juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Works: but it's certain, <hi>that by Works no Fleſh can be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied;</hi> no, tho they be the Works of the Law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20. <hi>By the deeds of the Law there ſhall no Fleſh be juſtified.</hi> If not by the Deeds of the Law, which were not only contrived by infinite Wiſdom, but bore the impreſs of God's terrible Majeſty upon them, and were diſpenſed and given from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> in pure Goodneſs to <hi>Iſrael:</hi> How much leſs ſhall Man be juſtified by Works de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed by Men, and founded upon no better warrant than humane Authority? It is alſo certain that Man is become culpable, and liable by Sin to the ſtroke of God's juſt Diſpleaſure, and therefore under an abſolute neceſſity of being juſtified from Sin, in order to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45045:4"/>his avoiding Miſery, and injoying Bleſſedneſs: which Bleſſedneſs, in the beginning, progreſs, and firſt ſteps of it, ſtands in God's good Will towards ſinners; but more perfectly in his free and full diſcharging us from the imputation of Sin, through the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which is in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And this was the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Opinion of the Men of God of old, as well as of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in our words, as is evident by his referring to the Prophet <hi>David</hi>'s Teſtimony, recorded in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.1, 2. So that it's no new Doctrin or novel thing, but what hath been, is, and will be believed to the end of the World, <hi>That the Man is Bleſſed unto whom the Lord imputes not Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words we have theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) A Bleſſedneſs pronounced, <hi>Bleſſed is:</hi> a Happineſs conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a ſure ſecurity from all Evil, but more eſpecially the evil of eternal Death, and an aſſurance of all Good and eternal Life.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) You have the ſubject of this Bleſſedneſs, <hi>the Man.</hi> And that you may know who this Man is, the Apoſtle deſcribes him by his Privilege, <hi>To whom the Lord will not impute Sin;</hi> a privilege peculiar to thoſe that are and ſhall be Happy. <hi>Bleſſed is the Man unto whom the Lord will not impute Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) The time when Man comes to be ſtated in this Bleſſedneſs; and that is in the very inſtant that God ceaſes to impute Sin. There is not any thing that Man injoys, which can render him Bleſſed, whilſt God charges Sin upon him; therefore <hi>Bleſſed is the Man:</hi> mark, he <hi>is</hi> Bleſſed; not <hi>ſhall be,</hi> but <hi>is,</hi> in the preſent tenſe; he <hi>is,</hi> and therefore <hi>ſhall be</hi> Bleſſed —</p>
            <p>We ſhall briefly enquire, 1. What we are to underſtand by the <hi>Lord's not imputing Sin.</hi> 2. Who by <hi>the Man to whom the Lord will not impute Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) By the <hi>Lord's not imputing Sin,</hi> we muſt underſtand a free Act of Grace in God, which Man of himſelf neither hath, nor ever could have deſerved, being utterly unable to ſatisfy that Juſtice he had by Sin offended, or appeaſe that Wrath which his Sin had kindled. Never could Man by his own procurement have reſcued himſelf from that Puniſhment and Miſery he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd by Sin; therefore we ſay, Not to impute, is an act of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in God, expreſt in his not charging Sin upon the ſinners ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, ſo as to exact ſatisfaction of the Debt from the Treſpaſſer,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45045:4"/>nor to puniſh the ſinner with eternal Miſery, in want of ſuch ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, of his own procurement.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) By the <hi>Lord's not imputing Sin,</hi> we may underſtand a free Act of Love and Kindneſs in God, in pardoning and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving Sin, as to the eternal Puniſhment of it. As when a Creditor is pleaſed of mere Mercy to forgive a poor Debtor his Debt juſtly due to him; in ſuch caſe he will not impute the Debt, nor charge it to account: or when a Governor forgives the fault of a Child or Servant, he will not impute the Crime, nor puniſh him for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Who is this Man to whom the Lord will not impute Sin. I conceive it is, (1.) Believing Man. (2.) Infant Man.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) God will not impute Sin to <hi>Believing Man.</hi> Every Man and Woman that in truth believes in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, may reſt with the greateſt Confidence in this Grace of God, who is ſaid to be <hi>the Juſtifier of every one that believeth in Jeſus,</hi> Rom. 3.26. &amp; 4.3, 4, 5. To which you have the concurrent Teſtimony of all the Prophets, in that ſummary Account given us by St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which is, <hi>that whoever believes in the name of Chriſt, ſhall receive the Remiſſion of Sin,</hi> Acts 10.43. So that none, as I know of, in the leaſt doubt the truth of this, that believing Man is privileged by, and intereſted in the Grace of God; and that he is not the Man to whom the Lord will impute Sin. But,</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) By <hi>the Man to whom God will not impute Sin,</hi> we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>Infant Man.</hi> The little Infant, the new born Babe, is ſtiled <hi>Man</hi> in Scripture Phraſe, and that truly, becauſe ſuch a one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of the whole nature of Man, tho unable to exert and put forth it ſelf in ſuch Actions (by reaſon of its natural Weakneſs and Impotency) as are proper to Men in a grown State, who are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of exerciſing their Underſtanding and Power in things they are imploy'd about. But this incapacity of Infants being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and common to all Men, deprives them no more of the name than the nature of <hi>Man:</hi> therefore <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaking of the frailty of humane Life, ſaith, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.1, 2. <hi>Man that is born of a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is of few days, and full of Miſery; he cometh up, and is cut down like a Flower:</hi> ſignifying that all the days of Man from his Birth to his Death, in number, are but very few; and as the Flower ſometimes is no ſooner blown but it's cut down, ſo Man ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times no ſooner breaths in the Air, but he falls into the Duſt; is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45045:5"/>no ſooner taken from the Womb, but he is laid in the Grave. But notwithſtanding his continuance here is ſo very ſhort, yet in his Infant ſtate he is truly ſtiled <hi>Man:</hi> And ſo our Lord in <hi>John</hi> 16.21. ſaith, <hi>A Woman in travail hath ſorrow, becauſe her Hour is come; but as ſoon as ſhe is delivered of the Child, ſhe remembreth no more her anguiſh, for joy a Man is born into the World.</hi> And that all Infants living or dying, whilſt ſuch, are the Subjects of the Bleſſedneſs in our Text, will I truſt no leſs appear if, void of all prejudice, we will conſider,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Man in his Infant State is a Sinner only by imputation, not by any choice, conſent, or act of his own, whereby he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſt any Law of God. For all Sin is the tranſgreſſion of a Law, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.4. But in that ſenſe dying Infants are not Sinners, God never aſſigning them a Law whereto they ſhould have regard, by any Command of his that I know of: And certain I am, where there is no Law, Sin is not imputed, as our Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.13. That Sin is imputed to Infants ſo far, as to bring them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of Death, I confeſs; and even ſo Sin is imputed unto Believers, for they die as well as others: But ſince there is no Law given to Infants, we ſoberly affirm, Sin is not imputed to them, to condemn them eternally to the torments of Hell Fire; and that is what we propoſe to clear upon this Occaſion: Which is further evident, if we conſider,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the degree to which God has exalted his Grace and Mercy in Chriſt the Second <hi>Adam,</hi> is not inferior, but rather above the pitch and degree whereto he exalted his Juſtice in condemning all in the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi> Juſtice makes no more than <hi>All</hi> Sinners in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> upon his tranſgreſſion; and Grace makes no leſs than <hi>All</hi> righteous in Chriſt Jeſus, or through his Righteouſneſs imputed: <hi>For,</hi> Rom. 5.18. <hi>as by the Offence of one, Judgment came upon all Men to condemnation; even ſo by the Righteouſneſs of one the free Gift came upon all Men to juſtification of Life.</hi> If up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all that believe, who have ſinned after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Tranſgreſſion, then much more upon them who have not ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; becauſe the preheminence is given to the free Gift of Grace by Chriſt, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.14, 15. intimating, that if <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin was efficacious enough to make all men Sinners, the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, which is God's own Righteouſneſs, is much more effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45045:5"/>to make them righteous. And truly with reverence we may demand, How can God himſelf expreſs the extent of his Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in terms more poſitive and intelligible than he doth here? And I am very certain, we neither have nor ever had any reaſon to ſuſpect him as inſincere, or to call in queſtion the truth of his Allegation. No, his Word is an exact draught of his Mind; and what he ſays, he means. As we all believe Infants were condemned in <hi>Adam,</hi> there's as good reaſon to believe 'em juſtified in Chriſt, and ſuch to whom the Lord will not impute Sin. Which will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appear if we conſider,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, in becoming a Propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for the Sin of Infants; not only for actual, but original Sin; not only for the Sins of the Adult and Believer, but of the Infant alſo. Had Chriſt been ſaid to be a Propitiation for the Sins of Believers only, it might have ſtruck our hopes into a ſtagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſture, with reference to the eternal State of our dying Babes; unleſs Foederal Holineſs ſo much talked or by ſome, or the Faith of immediate Parents, could have reliev'd them againſt the condemning Sin of our remote Parents. But if that were ſo, the greateſt part of Infants are and muſt be unavoidably miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as they are the Off-ſpring of Unbelievers, which the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the World are. Nay, it may on good ground be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectur'd, that one half of thoſe who profeſs themſelves Church-Members, are but little better, ſince our bleſſed Saviour compares the Kingdom of Heaven to ten Virgins, of whom five were wiſe, and five were fooliſh, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.1. But, bleſſed be God, we have a better Bottom to build our hopes upon, as to the eternal State of dying Babes, than ſuch ſandy Foundations as thoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſt's expiating and doing away the Sins of the World by the Sacrifice of himſelf. And this <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> had an eye to when he ſaw Chriſt coming, and pointed at him, ſaying, <hi>Behold the Lamb of God which taketh away the Sin of the World;</hi> enough ſure to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve all Doubts, and to ſtop every mouth for ever from contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting what we have alledged, That God imputes not Sin to the eternal condemnation of dying Infants; ſince Chriſt died for them, for them indefinitely and without exception.</p>
            <p>May we not as warrantably queſtion, whether Chriſt died at all, as to ſcruple, much leſs to deny, that he took away the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45045:6"/>guilt of Original Sin by the Oblation of himſelf; ſince he is ſaid thereby to take away the Sin of the World? Is there any one actual Sin in the World, that ſo generally and univerſally extends it ſelf, as to deprave and corrupt all Fleſh, Old and Young, Saint and Sinner, Chriſtian and Pagan? I confeſs, with grief and ſorrow, profane Swearing is very rife; Lying and Diſſimulation is very common; Pride, Covetouſneſs, Envy and Hatred, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Uncleanneſs, Violence, Murder, and profaning the Sabbath of the Lord, is very predominant: yet none of theſe things are univerſal; that which is common with one, is abhor'd by another; as the covetous Man cannot endure the approach of Pride, Luxury, and Prodigality. But were any, or all of theſe Sins of a univerſal Extent, ſo as to corrupt all capable of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them, of what Sex and of what Nation ſoever; yet our Infant Race is ſafe, and out of all poſſibility of being ſtained by them, or being brought under the power of any of them, from their utter incapacity to commit any of thoſe things by which the Wrath of God is brought upon the Children of Diſobedience, and them only. For if no Sin can be intended by the Sin of the World, but Original Corruption, then the Immaculate Lamb of God hath atoned for that, and taken it away; ſo that it ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be of efficacy and power to condemn a dying Infant, any more than it ſhall be of force to condemn a true Believer; the ſame reaſon being rendred for the one, as for the other, by the Apoſtle <hi>John,</hi> who ſpeaking of Chriſt, ſaith, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.2. <hi>He is the Propitiation for our Sins; and not for ours only, but for the Sins of the whole World.</hi> Mark, not only for <hi>ours,</hi> in which term he includes with himſelf all true Believers, of what Rank ſoever, high or low, rich or poor, reſpected or deſpiſed in the World, whoſe Sins are done away by Chriſt's atoning for them: But the Apoſtle adds, <hi>for the Sins of the whole World:</hi> Not of the whole World, as it conſiſts of habitual and voluntary Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as Swearers, Drunkards, Idolaters, Adulterers, and the like; for ſuch lie under the heavy charge and imputation of Sin, until by Faith in Chriſt, repentance from dead Works, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Goſpel, they ſhall, by the Grace of God, obtain Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity. Therefore the whole World, conſider'd in an Infant ſtate, and no other, can be intended by the Apoſtle; whereby
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45045:6"/>the eternal bleſſedneſs of dying Infants is ſecured; ſince God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of Grace, through the Righteouſneſs and Death of his Son, hath acquitted and diſcharged Infant Man from the imputation of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin, ſo as that he ſhall not periſh eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally for it. But in caſe Man ſurvives his Infant ſtate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts Guilt by voluntary tranſgreſſion in his own Perſon, as you and I have done, and be not renewed by Repentance from dead Works, and juſtified by Faith in our Lord Jeſus, according to the Tenour of the Goſpel, then we muſt periſh unavoidably and eternally; not for <hi>Adam</hi>'s Sin, but for ſuperadded Sins, Sins of our own againſt the Law of Grace, and the Love of a Redeemer. Thus God is clear from the death of his Creatures, and Sinners the alone Authors of their own deſtruction, according to the Scriptures. But for ſuch Infants as ſurvive not their Infant-ſtate, we conclude they are bleſſed, becauſe God will not impute Sin unto them; as appears, not only from the Law of Grace, but,</p>
            <p n="4">4. From the Law of Equity and Righteouſneſs. The Judg of the whole Earth muſt do right; he cannot but do ſo; he may as well ceaſe to be, as ceaſe to be righteous in all or any of his Miniſtrations and Procedures. Men may be rigorous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, cruel and prepoſterous; but God cannot be ſo; it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his Nature, and repugnant to that Law by which he will act and govern himſelf in all his proceedings with Man. Now I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all Men of common ſenſe and underſtanding, tho but of a ſmall meaſure of ingenuity and honeſty, whether it be conſiſtent with the common Rules of Juſtice and Equity among Men, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Innocent with the Nocent; the Faultleſs with the Guilty? Were it your own caſe, could you think ſo? Nay, that the Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal's Offence ſhould be charged upon you, and the Offender him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf go free? The latter of theſe all Men would decry, as high injuſtice, and a prepoſterous proceeding. But ſo it is in the caſe in hand, (reſerving that only Inſtance of Chriſt's ſuffering for us, and in our ſtead, by the deſignation of his Father, and as an evidence of his good Will to us.) We have not only God charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sin of <hi>Adam</hi> upon his whole Poſterity; wherein he is perfectly juſt, <hi>Adam</hi> conſidered as our common Head, and we all in his Loins ſtanding or falling in and with him, but letting <hi>Adam</hi> go free, and inflicting eternal puniſhment on his Seed: But with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45045:7"/>we may demand, What makes vain Man to imagine that God will diſcharge <hi>Adam</hi> the actual Offender, giving him imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately upon his Fall the promiſe of a Saviour, and yet bind the guilt of that Sin upon the greateſt part of his innocent Poſterity, who could neither avoid nor prevent it, to their inevitable ruin and eternal deſtruction? A Conception moſt unworthy of God, and his dealing with Men! For whatever Grace and Favour <hi>Adam</hi> received in ſo early a Promiſe of a Saviour, he received it as well for his Poſterity, as for himſelf; and as we had been repreſented by him under the diſadvantages of the Fall, ſo he being ſtill in the ſtation of a publick Perſon, matters were negotiated with him as our common Head, for the intitling us to the promiſed Saviour, as well as before he, and we in him, did ſo fall.</p>
            <p>The untoward Jews entertain'd ſuch a conceit as this of God, inſomuch that by the vent they gave it in their Diſcourſes, it was taken up as a Proverb in <hi>Iſrael, That the Fathers had eaten ſowr Grapes, and the Childrens teeth were ſet on edg,</hi> Ezek. 18.2. But doth God take this kindly at their hands, to repreſent him ſo unequal in his proceedings, as to puniſh the Innocent with the Guilty? No, he reſents it with great indignation and diſpleaſure, abhorring the thoughts they had of him, and the meaſure by which they repreſented him, as manifeſtly reflecting on the Goodneſs of his Nature, and the Juſtice of thoſe Rules and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws of Righteouſneſs by which he proceeded. Wherefore he ſolemnly declares, and that upon Oath, <hi>That thenceforth they ſhould have no more any occaſion to uſe it as a Proverb: As I live, ſaith the Lord God, all Souls are mine; as the Soul of the Father is mine, ſo alſo the Soul of the Son is mine; but the Soul that ſinneth, it ſhall die,</hi> as you read in the 3d and 4th Verſes. How poſitive and plain is the Lord in theſe terms, to ſatisfy all, and to rectify <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi>'s miſtake, whoſe Notions and ill-form'd Apprehenſions had been very unworthy of him, and who had without any ground conceiv'd him rigid and cruel. Therefore, <hi>Iſrael,</hi> change your Opinion of me; think of me no more as inequitable in my judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial proceedings with Man; I tell you again, <hi>The Soul that ſinneth ſhall die; the Son ſhall not bear the Iniquity of the Father,</hi> and ſo on, in the 20th Verſe—And this Juſtice and Righteouſneſs of God's dealings, is abundantly illuſtrated in that Paſſage, wherein
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45045:7"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> expreſſes great tenderneſs and ſtrong affection to ſinning and revolting <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in his interceſſion with God for them. His Love inclin'd him willingly to be made a Sacrifice for them that had ſinned, rather than God ſhould caſt off all regard for 'em, and enter the Liſts as an Enemy againſt them: <hi>Lord,</hi> ſays <hi>Moſes, if thou wilt not pardon thy People, blot me, I pray thee, out of the Book which thou haſt written,</hi> Exod. 32.32. To which the Lord, replies, as it were, No, no, <hi>Moſes,</hi> thou haſt not ſinned; and tho thou haſt ſufficiently expreſſed thy love to an undeſerving People, yet ſhould I do as thou deſireſt, it would be to act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Rules of perfect Equity and Juſtice, from which I will not, I cannot ſwerve; and therefore it is only they that <hi>have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt me, that I will blot out of my Book,</hi> as verſ. 33. My love to my People hath been very great, expreſt by manifold acts of kindneſs; but in caſe they ſin, as they have now done, my Juſtice and Faithfulneſs will not let them go unpuniſhed; much leſs puniſh thee an innocent Perſon for their ſin, and acquit them thereupon from the ſin and puniſhment due to it. From all which it's evident, that God will not impute Sin to dying Infants, to their eternal condemnation; and that in both theſe reſpects, <hi>that Man is bleſſed,</hi> Infant, as well as believing Man, <hi>unto whom the Lord will not impute Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctrine from the words is, <q rend="inline">That he, and he alone is bleſſed, whoſe Sin is not imputed; and that dying Infants are aſſuredly bleſſed on that account.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſs there are many in the World, who from the proſperity of their preſent ſtate and condition, think all is well with them; they are not under wracking pain, nor pinching poverty; they have their Wants ſupply'd, and it may be more than their hearts can deſire, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.4, 5, 7. The Language of whoſe Hearts is the ſame with that of <hi>Babylon</hi>'s, Rev. 18.7. <hi>I ſit as a Queen, and ſhall ſee no ſorrow:</hi> whereas their Sun may he declining; and, as <hi>Zephar</hi> ſays, <hi>Job</hi> 20.5, 6, 7. <hi>their Proſperty is very ſhort;</hi> the remainder of their days may be fill'd with trouble, perplexity, and diſappointment, and nothing remain but a ſad proſpect of mourning and ſorrow in utter darkneſs, if not prevented by a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45045:8"/>timely and hearty Repentance. All is not Gold that gliſters: 'tis too common for Man to miſtake his own ſtate, and to think with <hi>Laodicea,</hi> Rev. 3.17. becauſe of their full enjoyment of this World's Wealth, accompanied with a profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion, <hi>that they are Rich and have need of nothing,</hi> when as in truth <hi>they are wretched, miſerable, poor, blind, and naked.</hi> The rich Man in the Goſpel was no leſs miſtaken at laſt as to his own ſtate and condition.</p>
            <p>Moſt certain it is, that Nature has not power to endow us with Features ſo amiable, and Faculties ſo excellent, as to inſure us of Bleſſedneſs. The greateſt Beauty is oft ſpoiled by a fit of Sickneſs, as the Small Pox, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſometimes not only defaced, but turned into a frightful Viſage by Death, whether natural or violent, as <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s was, whoſe Beauty ſurpaſſed that of Women. What is Wit but a Flaſh? and tho it be excellent and deſervedly coveted by all; yet, alas, how ſoon is the ſharpeſt Wit ſpoiled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd by Melancholy or Phrenſy! And as of theſe, ſo it may be concluded of all the reſt of Nature's Endowments; which loudly proclaim that true Bleſſedneſs is not in them.</p>
            <p>Nor is it in the Goods of Fortune. I confeſs Fortune may render you very proſperous, in having the Advantage of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable and beneficial gales; but the moſt ſhe can do for you, is to raiſe you by the wings of Fame, exalt you to the higheſt pitch of Honour, ſet upon your Heads a fading Diadem, and waft you into the port of your wiſh'd for Poſſeſſion; Wealth enabling you to accommodate your ſelves with every thing deſirable to the Heart, and delightful in the Eyes of vain Man, as in the caſe of <hi>Solomon:</hi> But it's not in Fortune to make you happy, tho ſhe would at once empty her ſelf to fill you. If Crowns or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms could make Men happy, then <hi>Saul, Ahab</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had been bleſſed. Neither can Honour or Wiſdom; elſe <hi>Haman</hi> and <hi>Ahitophel</hi> had been Bleſſed. Nor can Riches and great Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions; if they could, the young, and rich Man in the Goſpel had been bleſſed, who from his increaſing Goods thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a very happy Man: he ſang a <hi>Requiem</hi> to his Soul, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed himſelf with a <hi>Come, eat, drink and be merry, thou haſt Goods laid up for many Years,</hi> Luke 12.19. as if he had ſaid, <q rend="inline">Come, Soul, forbear to weary and perplex thy ſelf with plod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45045:8"/>contriving, and projecting Means and Artifices for the gaining of more; ceaſe to weary thy ſelf by toilſome Labour; take thine eaſe, thy fill of Pleaſure; eat, drink, and be merry; thou haſt Goods laid up for many Years.</q> But notwithſtanding the great Advantage he had of other Men in appearance, he was in truth no wiſer than a Fool, nor happier by his truſting in thoſe things, than one miſerable beyond all Expreſſion; as is evident from the Lord's own eſtimate of him, and what he ſays to him in the 20th Verſe: <hi>And God ſaid, Thou Fool, this Night ſhall thy Soul be required of thee; then whoſe ſhall theſe things be which thou haſt provided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither can the higheſt attainments in Tongues and Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, make Men Bleſſed; elſe <hi>Herod</hi> had been happy, who in his Oration to the People, delivered himſelf ſo exquiſitely, that they concluded it rather to be the Voice of a God, than of a Man, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.22. Alſo on this foot of Account the Learned Greeks had been Bleſſed, whoſe attainments in the Learning of the Schools were ſuch, as raiſed them above the having any ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable eſteem of the Wiſdom of God; accounting Chriſt, in the miniſtration of the Goſpel, to be but Fooliſhneſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23.</p>
            <p>Now were it poſſible for Man to poſſeſs himſelf of moſt, or all theſe good things at once, he might notwithſtanding be of all Men the moſt Miſerable, as may be concluded from that ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing and direful outcry to the weighty Hills and Mountains to fall upon them, and cruſh them, as it were, into nothing, ſo that they might be but hid from the Preſence of God, and the Wrath of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6.16. But who were theſe that thus courted the Hills and Mountains to fall on them? Were they any other than the ſilly ſhrubs of the Earth, poor Men, Men of a mean Figure in the World? Yes, for the 15th Verſe tells you, that they were <hi>Kings of the Earth,</hi> that is, ſuch Kings only whoſe Sins the Lord had marked and imputed, upon their living re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant, and walking in a courſe that ran counter to thoſe Laws which the King of Heaven and Earth had given them, and by the Conduct whereof they ſhould have order'd all their Affairs, in obedience to him their Rightful Lord and Soveraign. With theſe alſo you find ranked <hi>great Men, rich Men, mighty Men,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45045:9"/>and <hi>chief Captains;</hi> which may ſerve as a Memorandum to the Rich and Mighty of this World, that they do not cruſh the Poor, nor hurt the Needy; nor by their Power and Auſterity, unjuſtly force the Poor from their Right; nor by the uſe of Violence and Oppreſſion increaſe their Wealth; inſulting over the diſtreſſed, like that Imperious Pope, of whom I have read, that trod upon the Emperor's Neck, to help himſelf on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back. For a day of Accounts will come, when ſuch will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced with great Horror and Dread, that it is not in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Riches and Royalties to make Men Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>And on the other hand, there is no Diſtreſs ſo great, nor Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty ſo extreme, nor Affliction ſo deep, as to render that Man miſerable, whoſe Sin is not imputed. Such a Man is taught to believe that his preſent Evils, with reſpect to his Afflictions, ſhall work for his good, and turn to his Advantage, by the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of God's good Providence, which is ingaged for him. Elſe the Royal Prophet had never proclaim'd it good for him that he was Afflicted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71. Nay further, by Faith in the Promiſes, the Good whereof is that Man's Portion alone whoſe Sin is not imputed, he is helped to peirce the Clouds of the thickeſt darkneſs, and look into that delightſome Region of Heaven it ſelf, and there behold the ſmiles of a loving Father towards him; the endeavours of a wiſe, faithful, and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Advocate for him, yielding him ſuch a taſte and ſenſe of the ſweetneſs of Divine Love, as raiſes him above the ſenſe and bitterneſs of Affliction. It was this that made St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> rejoice, that they were counted worthy to ſuffer Stripes for the Lord Jeſus. It was this that made St. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> tho laden with heavy Shackles, and their feet made faſt in the Stocks, to ſing the Praiſes of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 16. 'Tis not the Evil Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, or Indiſpoſition that attends our Bodies or Intereſts in the World, that can make the Man whoſe Sin is not imputed, unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py or miſerable; for the wiſe Man tells us, <hi>That the Spirit of a Man ſuſtains his Infirmities,</hi> Prov. 18.14. A Man may have a ſound Spirit in a weak and ſickly Body; a free and chearful Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in a Body cloſely confin'd, and oblig'd to undergo the laſt Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities of Art and Phyſick, as bliſtering, blooding, cupping, and diſmembring; nay, in a Body ſinking by the power and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valency
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45045:9"/>of a Diſtemper into diſſolution, which of all things is moſt dreadful to humane nature. But under ſuch a Circumſtance, what matter of Joy would it be to a Man to have his weak and languiſhing Body reſtored to a ſound and healthful frame and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit? for which, how are Phyſicians courted, their aſſiſtance ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited; and ſome Men do let their Gold fly as if they had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard unto it. But to have Sin pardoned, and be freed from the imputation of its guilt, is much rather, and more truly a ground of joy to the Soul, tho dwelling in a Body weak and impotent; as is certain from what our Bleſſed Saviour ſays to the Man ſick of the Palſy, <hi>Son, be of good chear, thy Sins are forgiven thee,</hi> Mat. 9.2. Mark, it's not <hi>be of good chear, for thou art made whole;</hi> but <hi>thy Sins are forgiven thee:</hi> This is enough to make the Lame to walk, the Deaf to hear, the Blind to ſee; here's that which is ſufficient to turn our Weeping into Laughter, our Mourning into Rejoicing, our Death into Life; and to ſettle us in a belief that he, and he alone is bleſſed, whoſe Sin is not imputed. Now ſuch are bleſſed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. In Life, as thereby God takes the Children of Men into a ſtate of Grace and Favour with himſelf: For God's not imputing Sin, is the removal of that which begot the difference, and hath maintain'd the diſtance betwixt him and his Creatures, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.2. Of all Evils, Sin is the greateſt, becauſe it hath not the leaſt mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Good in it to make it tolerable; nor doth it produce the leaſt good to any Creature. It was Sin that turned the Angels out of Heaven, that caſt Man out of Paradiſe, that brought the Curſe upon the Creation, and Wrath upon Sinners. To be freed therefore from ſo great an Evil, is one part of our Happineſs; and that which compleats it, is God's taking us into Favour, <hi>whoſe Favour is better than Life,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſays, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.3. in whoſe Favour you may reſt aſſured of all Advantages neceſſary to render you happy in this Life, as the ſupply of your Wants, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9, 10. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.3. protection from Dangers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.18. &amp; 34.10. guidance in all your Ways, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.23, &amp;c. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.6: ſtrength againſt Temptation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. a ſanctified uſe of Afflictions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. and deliverance out of Trouble, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.19, 22. Such unto whom the Lord imputes not Sin, may no leſs reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of Peace: <hi>For being juſtified by Faith, we have Peace with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45045:10"/>God through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 5.1. Which Peace of God will fill our hearts, and keep us in peace when others are in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and quiet, tho the World be in an uproar. And tho many are hurried to and fro by cutting Perplexities, fretting Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, and growing Fears, God will make their Habitations quiet reſting-places; there is ſcarcely any thing that ſhall offend and moleſt them, for Peace is always the ſure Effect and Fruit of Righteouſneſs to Juſtification, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.17, 18. As they have Peace and Proviſion, ſo they ſhall have every thing neceſſary to render them bleſſed in Life, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. for God will withhold no good thing from them to whom he will not impute Sin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are bleſſed alſo in Death, becauſe God's not imputing Sin is to diſpoil Death of all Power that otherwiſe might render it hurtful to us. Guilt, which is Death's fiery Sting, is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and he ceaſes to be a King of Terrors. They fear him not, how terrible ſoever he may be in his march towards them. They whoſe Sin is not imputed, are ready to receive and entertain him, knowing that in this his laſt and moſt violent Effort, he is like to go away with a poor Conqueſt; the greateſt execution he can do upon them, is to cut the Thread of Life, and ſend their frail, brittle, weak, and ſickly Bodies to the duſt, for a while to ſleep in the Grave, whilſt bleſſed Angels wait the fatal ſtroak to take the fleeting Soul into their embraces, and with Wings extended car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them ſwiftly into the happineſs of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Boſom. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs there is reaſon enough for the Man, whoſe Sin and Guilt is bound upon him, to dread the approach, and tremble at the ſight of ſuch an Enemy, arm'd with nothing but Terrors, and ready to wound the Soul with his flaming and ſiery Sting, ready to cut the thin-ſpun Thread of Life; which when done, he is violently ſeized by ſome of the Infernal Crew, and hurried un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably to the Confines and Region of utter Darkneſs, to ſuffer the Pains of Eternal Fire. O that Sinners would timely conſider of this, to break off every vicious Courſe by Repentance, laying hold on the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt by a lively Faith, expreſt by ſincere obedience to the Commands of the Goſpel, leſt their Sin haſten Death, and in death proves their ruin! But Death is ſo far from being hurtful to the Man whoſe Sin is not imputed, that it is truly neceſſary, as the only means by which bleſſed Souls are conveyed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45045:10"/>from ſojourning in theſe tottering houſes of Clay, to live for ever with their Saviour in that houſe and building not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens. This made holy <hi>Paul</hi> chuſe <hi>rather to die than live, that he might be with Chriſt, which was beſt of all, Phil.</hi> 1.23. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 2. So that the Man to whom the Lord imputes not Sin, is bleſſed in Death; and not only ſo, but in the</p>
            <p>3d place, Such are bleſſed after death, in that death lands them ſafe on that ſhore, where they ſhall for ever rejoice in celebrating the Memory of the Grace of God in not imputing Sin unto them. Their entrance into Heaven is made ſure, and every thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved that otherwiſe might obſtruct it, who ſhall there be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and happy in the higheſt degree; if we conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The perfect freedom they ſhall have in Heaven from all Evil. On Earth holy Souls have often the greateſt ſhare of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and Trouble; as one Link follows another in the Chain, or as one Wave another, ſo <hi>deep calleth unto deep,</hi> Pſal. 42.7. Here with <hi>Lazarus</hi> they have their evil things, Poverty, Pain, Sickneſs, Sores, Croſſes, Troubles, Temptations, Afflictions, Diſeaſes, and Death; but all theſe evil things and more ſhall be left behind them in death, and in Heaven they ſhall have no ſenſe of them: <hi>For God ſhall wipe away all tears from their eyes, and there ſhall be no more death, neither ſorrow, nor crying; neither ſhall there be any more pain, for the former things are paſſed away,</hi> Rev. 21.4. Tho it will be quite otherwiſe with the Wicked, who here on Earth had their good things, but ſhall then have their evil things; they ſhall no more enjoy the precious things their Souls luſted af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and the things that were dainty and goodly being departed, they ſhall find them no more at all, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.14. no, not one drop of Water to cool their flaming Tongues. Such as affect Sin here, tho God ſo earneſtly ſollicites them to the contrary, muſt, for their contempt of his Grace, be content to lie down in everlaſting burnings, where without relief they muſt roll in tormenting flames, and ſhall have no reſt day nor night, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.8. The Wicked then ſhall have their evil things, but the Godly their good things, who ſhall be for ever raiſed above the ſenſe of any thing afflicting: and in this reſpect they are bleſſed.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:45045:11"/>
            <p>Secondly, The Man whoſe Sin is not imputed, is bleſſed after Death, conſidering he is then put into ſuch a condition, as ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders it utterly impoſſible for him to forfeit this Grace, or to loſe ſo deſirable a Happineſs as that of Heaven is. Serious and devout Souls on Earth are, or at leaſt ought to be fearful of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, than of loſing the Favour of God, or that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not his Grace in vain. O the Fears and Tears, the Cares and Prayers, the Watchings and Strivings of the truly pious! all which ſpeak forth the poſſbility of it, as well as the many ſad Inſtances we have upon Record, to the end we may not luſt as they luſted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.6. but avoid the Rocks on which they ſplit. But ſuch is the ſtate of the Godly in Heaven after Death, that it renders their Abiding certain, ſtable, and unalterable. There is no Evil there, much leſs any Sin; not a Temptation to incline the Will to offend; no, both Will and Power will be wanting in Heaven to make a forfeiture of it. There is a Gulf fixed betwixt the ſaved and the damned, which makes it impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for them to change their Stations, or to paſs from one place to the other, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25, 26. But,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That which compleats the Bleſſedneſs of the Man, to whom the Lord will not impute Sin after Death, is the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs he ſhall actually and for ever enjoy in his Perſon in Heaven: There he ſhall behold the Face of God and the Lamb; there he ſhall partake of the Fulneſs of God's Glory, be ſatisfied with the delights of his Preſence, and the Pleaſures and Treaſures that be at his right hand. There the Righteous ſhall not only hear the Holy Quire of Bleſſed Angels and Saints triumphant, warble forth the Praiſes of God, but ſhall join with mouths full of Hallelujaths to God and the Lamb, in a grateful memory of that kindneſs the Lord ſhewed them, in not imputing Sin unto them. There they ſhall be ſet upon ſtable and fixed Thrones, their Heads crown'd with unfading Diadems, and their Faces ſhine with rays of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable Glory, with greater luſter and brightneſs than the Sun in the Firmament. In a word, it is a Bleſſedneſs too great to be expreſſed by the Tongue, or to be conceiv'd by the Heart of man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. The moſt raiſed Imagination cannot reach it. Thus we have ſhewed you that he, and he alone is bleſſed, whoſe Sin is not imputed.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:45045:11"/>
            <p>If this be the aſſured Happineſs of ſuch unto whom the Lord will not impute Sin, and more, as is ſuggeſted; it may be worth our inquiry how we may come to know certainly that we have obtained Impunity, that this Act of Grace in the High Court of Heaven is paſt for us, that our Names are there inrolled, that we are the Men and Women to whom the Lord imputes no Sin, and are conſequently bleſſed.</p>
            <p>Sirs, 'Tis certain there are Properties and Characters common to ſuch as are thus privileged; and among many, I will name four, which we ſhall find common to all on whom the Lord char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges no Sin. The</p>
            <p>Firſt is ſincere Love and Affection to God. As it is the Fruit of Divine Love to be freed from the Imputation of Sin, ſo 'tis the property of every bleſt Soul to love the Lord. The Law of his Mouth is the Law of Love and Kindneſs; his Soul is delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the contemplation of God's Love to him, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goes forth with ſtrong and hearty Love to him again. A Man ſenſible of the greatneſs of that Wrath from which he is deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, and the greatneſs of that Happineſs to which he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled, cannot but expreſs, with hearty Affection, the kind and reſpectful ſentiment he hath of ſuch Grace and Favour. From hence it was that <hi>David</hi> ingages himſelf to love the Lord, and declares his reſolution therein, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.1. <hi>I will,</hi> ſays he, <hi>love the Lord, becauſe he hath heard the Voice of my Supplication:</hi> He hath now put me into the injoyment of that which I have long, often, and earneſtly ſued unto him for, and which is in truth the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer of many Prayers; therefore I will love him. I cannot but love him; his Love conſtrains me to love him, becauſe he loved me firſt, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.19. And this is further evident from what our Bleſſed Saviour ſays in the Parable to <hi>Simon</hi> the Phariſee, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling us, That <hi>Mary loved much, becauſe her Sins, which were many, were forgiven her,</hi> Luke 7.47. God is in himſelf the only worthy Object of our Affection, as he is perfectly amiable, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lovely, were we not under an Obligation flowing from his Kindneſs in taking away our Sin; but where a Soul is under this Obligation, there will be a care to make ſome ſutable return of Love; and indeed our Love muſt be very great, if it bears any
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45045:12"/>proportion to the Love of God expreſt in his not imputing Sin unto us. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, Obedience to his Commands, without which 'tis not poſſible to know our ſelves to be privileged Perſons, nor ſhall we ever be able to read our Names written in the Roll of Heaven. There is no other way wherein we can expreſs the truth and ſtrength of our Love to God, than by obedience to his Commands, <hi>John</hi> 14.23, 24. All love, not ſo evidenced, is nothing but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation and mere pretence; neither is there any Command that a Man will boggle at, to whom the Lord imputes not Sin. A ſenſe of this Grace will wonderfully incline and quicken us to do his Will. <hi>Iſaiah</hi>'s Lips were no ſooner touched with a Coal from God's Altar, importing the purging and taking away his Sin, but it preſently diſpoſes him to God's Service: When the Voice ſaid, <hi>Who ſhall go for us?</hi> immediately the Prophet preſents himſelf, ſaying, <hi>Here am I, ſend me:</hi> I am now ready for any Errand, to ingage in any buſineſs for thy Glory, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.7, 8. If God is ſo kind to break our Fetters, and to unlooſe the Cords that bound us, and ſo ſet us at Liberty, it is not that we ſhould uſe our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty as an occaſion to the Fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13. and ſin with a higher hand againſt God, whoſe Grace abounds, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1, 2. but that we ſhould love the Lord our God, and ſerve him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12. which St. <hi>Paul</hi> did with all readineſs, not once conferring with Fleſh and Blood: He demur'd not, nor was diſcouraged by thoſe floods of Troubles, Tumults, Perils, Diſtreſſes, Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Perſecutions, that he might raiſe up againſt himſelf; none of theſe things hindred him from a vigorous ingaging in the Work of God's Service, but he was obedient to the Heavenly Viſion, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.19. And as it is thus evident, that Obedience is the Property of ſuch as are in truth thus privileged with the Grace of God: ſo I doubt not, but we who have ſome good ground to hope that we are bleſſed upon God's not imputing Sin unto us, have oftentimes avowed our ſelves to be the Lord's Servants, and to render him the Service he calls for at our hands. Which is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Sincere Obedience. Obedience without Sincerity, is no more that which God calls for, than a ſtinking Breath flowing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45045:12"/>from corrupt Lungs, is naturally ſweet, that is only made ſo by the help of ſome ſtrong Perfume in the Mouth, as we may learn from our Bleſſed Saviour's reprehending the Hypocriſy of the Jews, ſaying, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8. <hi>This People draws nigh unto me with their Mouth, and do honour me with their Lips; but their Hearts are far from me.</hi> Every Law of God calls for an inward as well as an outward conformity; it would be unworthy to put off God with the Shell and Husk of our Services, who requires Truth in the inward Parts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.6. And not only ſo, but,</p>
            <p n="2">2. God calls for Conſtancy in Obedience. 'Tis not enough that we are obedient by fits and ſtarts, for a ſpurt and away, but that we abide and continue in the Work of the Lord. And what more reaſonable, than that we, who are always under the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of his Goodneſs, and benefits of his Grace, ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs conſtancy in our Obedience? Want of this was the procur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſe of the many miſeries and calamities that afflicted <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and as it could not go well with them becauſe of their inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſo it cannot go well with us till we be ſtedfaſt, immoveable, always abounding in the Work of the Lord, as is evident from the Lord's wiſhing that it were ſo with <hi>Iſrael, that it might go well with them and their Children for ever,</hi> Deut. 5.29. And,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord calls alſo for Univerſal Obedience. Partiality in God's Service will never characterize us to be ſuch whom he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, any more than it did King <hi>Saul</hi> in ſparing <hi>Agag</hi> King of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> with the beſt of their Sheep and Oxen, which God gave him commandment to deſtroy, as you may ſee at large in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. To do ſome things in Religion, which may bid fair to crown us with fame and reputation; inrolling our Names a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe who by Men are accounted devout, while we leave undone thoſe things which 'tis like if done, may prove to our coſt, and procure the contemptible eye and frowns of Men upon us, would be as arch Hypocriſy in us, as it was in the Scribes and Phariſees to tithe their Aniſe, Mint, and Cummin, while they omitted the more weighty matters of the Law, as Judgment, Mercy, and Faith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.23.</p>
            <p>Now as we would be univerſal, 'tis neceſſary that we be regular in our Obedience: for diſorder and confuſion in the Lord's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45045:13"/>will never evince us the Men to whom the Lord imputes not Sin. It would be Sin in us to neglect a due regard of the rules God hath given us for the right methodizing of our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as we might ſhew from that inſtance of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu</hi>'s crooked and prepoſterous proceeding in the Lord's work, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.1, 2. Therefore as <hi>Solomon</hi> aſcended his Throne by ſteps, ſo we in God's Service, muſt proceed from one Duty to another, and all in order, as we ſhall briefly demonſtrate.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) As all Men have ſinned (I mean the Adult) ſo it is in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the duty of all Men to repent, and to lie proſtrate at the foot of God's Mercy, as a poſture beſt becoming ſuch Traitors and Rebels as we have been: Nay, 'tis incumbent upon all to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, as inforced by the Authority of God's Law commanding. Tho God winked at the times of Ignorance, yet now he requires all Men every where to repent, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. Again, <hi>Repent, and be converted, that your Sins may be blotted out,</hi> Acts 3.19.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Upon a ſenſe of Sin, and our miſery by Sin, 'tis our Duty by a vigorous and lively Faith, to lay hold upon Jeſus Chriſt and his Righteouſneſs for our Juſtification, who is the alone Redeemer and reſtorer of loſt Creatures. If it be the demand of any poor Sinner, <hi>What they muſt do to be ſaved?</hi> the Anſwer is, <hi>Believe in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Acts 16.31. So alſo <hi>John</hi> 6.28, 29.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) Having repented of Sin, and profeſt Faith in Chriſt, and by the Grace of God in a good meaſure reformed our Lives, 'tis no leſs our Duty by God's Command to be Baptized or Dipped in Water, in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, as <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. And upon our Obedience to God herein, we have the pardon of Sin aſſured to us, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. and 8.37, 38. and 22.16. We confeſs with Grief that this Ordinance, through the corruption of Men, is become a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable, low, and contemptible thing in the eyes of the World, who are held in hand by too many of the Learned, with an Opinion that they were Baptized in their Infancy, altho in truth they were not, nor was it needful they ſhould: yet the generality of Men are contented to be thus put off with one thing for another, to wit, Rantiſm for Baptiſm. But let all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45045:13"/>have a care they do not entertain light Thoughts of this Duty, to a neglecting of it, ſince God hath been pleaſed to intail the pardon of Sin upon a conſcientious performance of it; and not only ſo, but it ſtates us in an undeniable Right to all the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges of the Church of Chriſt: into which being thus entred by Baptiſm, we are not there to reſt as if all our work was done; but</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) It remains that we there abide, attentively to hear, and diligently to learn what the Lord ſhall teach us from time to time to be his Will and our Duty; that by doing his Will, and ſuffering his Pleaſure, we may appear to be good proficients, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to ſuch a degree of Holineſs, as may render us Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to our holy Profeſſion, be ſutable to the holy Vocation wherewith we were called, and to the Place and Privileges wherein God hath ſtated us, and ſo may never want an Evidence to our Comfort, that we are thoſe to whom the Lord imputes no Sin. The</p>
            <p>Third Property common to ſuch, is a compaſſionate, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and charitable temper of Mind. The Mercy of God hath raiſed them to a good degree and pitch of Generoſity and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; they are like their Heavenly Father in a great meaſure, apt to forgive, not of a quarrelſome, injurious, and revenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Temper; not as it is with many, but a word and a blow; not for the taking their fellow Servants by the Throat, with ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour exacting the utmoſt farthing and ſatisfaction from, them. No: but under the influence of the divine Bounty; are ſweetly diſpoſed to forgive Wrongs, to paſs by Injuries and Offences, in imitation of a Meek and Holy Jeſus, and of his faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Stephen,</hi> who in Compaſſion to his very Perſecutors before his Death, ſeeing Heaven opened to him, prefer'd his Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to God, that he would not lay their Sin to their charge, as <hi>Acts</hi> 7.60. But the</p>
            <p>Fourth and laſt Property I ſhall name common to every Man to whom the Lord imputes not Sin, is that of Thankfulneſs. The deſign of his whole Life is to expreſs the gratitude of his Soul to God; the Language of his Heart is that of Praiſe, and his Mouth is full of Hallelujahs and thankful Acknowledgments of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45045:14"/>the divine Goodneſs: <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me bleſs his Holy Name, who forgiveth all thine Iniquities,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.1, 2, 3. And if here is not enough to ingage us in the unwearied celebrating of God's Praiſes, what will or can? ſince they whoſe Sins are not imputed, are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to a Happineſs above all expreſſion: and when once they have entred the Heavenly Region, and are ranged there among the Bleſſed, will think Eternity little enough to be ſpent in aſcribing Praiſe and Glory to God who ſits on the Throne, and to the Lamb, in diſcharging us from the Guilt and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Sin, and in ſtating us in ſo great, high, and laſting a Happineſs, as the fruit of his not imputing Sin: for, I ſay, <hi>Bleſſed is the Man unto whom the Lord imputes not Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We now proceed to ſhew you on this foot of Account, that dying Infants are Bleſſed, being ſuch on whom the Lord will not charge Sin to their eternal Condemnation. And truly I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but hope my work is more than half done, from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial deſires of our Hearts that it may be ſo. The thing is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly very deſirable, eſpecially to ſuch as have long mourned, (being doubtful in the matter) not knowing what the eternal State of their deceaſed Babes may be. To remove their fears, and ſatisfy all, I ſhall, tho the more briefly, becauſe of what has been ſaid already, labour to clear up the Safety and Happineſs of dying Infants, through the Grace of God in not imputing Sin unto them; and that from theſe Conſiderations.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Conſider the unparallel'd and incomparable Goodneſs of God towards all. There is no rank of Creatures, no not the ſilly Ant in the Earth, or Fly in the Air, but partakes of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Bounty and Goodneſs, being always under the beneficial influences of that God who is Gracious, Merciful, of Long ſuffering, abundant in Goodneſs and Truth, as he ſtiles him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6. And he is not ſo in himſelf only, but he is diffuſively ſo; he upholds and communicates of his goodneſs to all his Creatures: ſo ſays the Pſalmiſt, Pſalm 145.8, 9. <hi>The Lord is gracious and full of Compaſſion; ſlow to Anger, and of great Mercy. The Lord is good to all, and his tender Mercies are over all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45045:14"/>his Works.</hi> If over all, even the meaneſt of his Creatures; then why not over innocent and dying Babes, who never had either Will or Power in their own Perſons once to offend? Can there be thought a more meet object in all the World of the Goodneſs of God, than innocent and dying Infants, who have Souls more valuable than the whole World, and are capable of the joys of a bleſſed, or undergoing the Woes of a miſerable and doleful Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? Hath God in his goodneſs a care of every hair of your heads, ſo that not one ſhall fall to the ground without his permiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.29, 30. and ſhall he have no compaſſion nor tender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the precious Souls of dying Infants? I pray, in what ſenſe could the Royal Prophet in truth ſay, <hi>The Lord is good to all,</hi> if not in this ſenſe good to Infants, who it may be no ſooner breath, but die, and are violently hurried from the confines of the Womb, to the confines and region of Hell it ſelf, to ſuffer the puniſhment of Eternal Fire? Is this conſiſtent with Goodneſs it ſelf, to have no regard to ſo great and noble a Part of his Workmanſhip, as Man in his Infant-State is, and in which State he is but merely a paſſive Creature; and not only ſo, but to let him drop, nay to caſt him with indignation into thoſe Flames that were originally and intentionally prepared for the Devil and his Angels, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. for what they could not poſſibly avoid, and that without the leaſt Remedy? This is rather to ſtrip God of his Goodneſs, which by Man ought to be eſteemed the very Perfection of his Nature, who is ſo good, that <hi>in compariſon of him,</hi> as our Lord ſays, <hi>there is none good but God,</hi> Mat. 19.17.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) That dying Infants are bleſſed and happy, we may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured from Chriſt's dying for them. And ſuch is the virtue and efficacy of the Death and Blood of the Lord Jeſus, that by it the Salvation of all dying Infants is ſecured; elſe Chriſt in dying did not taſt Death for every Man, according to the intent and purpoſe of God in his Grace towards Man, as the Apoſtle de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. But that he taſted Death for every Man, is certain, ſince he is truly ſtiled <hi>the Saviour of all Men,</hi> tho more eſpecially of <hi>them that believe,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.10. it is not only of them that believe, but alſo of all Men. And ſo in <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.6. <hi>He gave himſelf a Ranſom for all.</hi> If for all, then for dying Babes; for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45045:15"/>who ſhall exclude them, ſince Chriſt hath by his Death expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and done away the Sin of the World? But enough of this, having toucht on it before.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) That dying Infants are bleſſed, is evident from the utter impoſſibility of its being otherwiſe: 'Tis not poſſible they ſhould periſh, ſince there is not any that can or will damn them; God will not, and Men cannot; they cannot damn themſelves, being under the Power of no Law; and <hi>where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion,</hi> Rom. 4.15. and where there is no Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, there is no Damnation, for that is the Wages of Sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</p>
            <p>Man cannot damn them. I confeſs Men may deſtroy them as to a temporal Life, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28. they may murder and ruin them in their Paſſion and Madneſs, or in their blind Zeal may make them Sacrifices to their Idols, as in the caſe of <hi>Moloch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Devil cannot damn them; at moſt he can but tempt, ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite, and allure, by ſuch Means and Arguments as he judges moſt likely to prevail. But who can be ſo weak as once to imagin that Satan ever levels his fiery Darts againſt innocent and dying Babes? They cannot rationally be the Subjects he ſollicits, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons he tempts, or the Tinder he drops his fiery Sparks upon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have no knowledg between Good and Evil, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.39. they diſcern not betwixt things that differ; they know not their right hand from their left, <hi>Jonah</hi> 4.11. nor have any power to chuſe the Good, and refuſe the Evil. Tho Parents ſhould be ſo wicked by their Sin and Apoſtacy, to forfeit their title to the happineſs of a promiſed <hi>Canaan,</hi> yet Parents cannot deſtroy their Childrens Right, by ſuch defection from God's Law, to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Celeſtial Region. No, thither are dying Infants bound, and haſtning under the happy advantages of Wind and Tide, let Men or Devils do what they can, as you may ſee to perfect ſatisfaction, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.30, 31. No interpoſition can hinder their paſſage, or obſtruct their entring the Port of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Bleſſedneſs—And as theſe cannot, ſo God will not damn them; you have his Promiſe to the contrary, and he is faithful to perform; beſides, Chriſt hath died for them, in whom they are made alive, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. But our</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:45045:15"/>
            <p>Fourth Conſideration is taken from the capacity and fitneſs of little Children for Heaven and Glory. Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt had ſo high an opinion of them, and their fitneſs, that he ſets them before his Diſciples as a Copy to write after, an Example to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, and as Perſons not only worthy, but neceſſary for them to reſemble; as appears by his taking and ſetting a little Child in the midſt of them, and with a ſolemn aſſeveration aſſerting, <hi>That except they be converted, and become as little Children, they ſhould not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> If little Children dying ſuch, do not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven, is it not moſt abſurd that our Lord ſhould ſo ſolemnly and expreſly injoin his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to become like them, in order to their entring into his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? Were it not ſo, that little Children have a ſitneſs for Heaven, Diſciples and Chriſtians in becoming like them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are moſt ſtrictly obliged, would thereby become unfit for Heaven and Glory. But,</p>
            <p>Fifthly and laſtly, That dying Infants are bleſſed, appears from as good Reaſon as we have to believe any thing for truth that is contain'd in all the Sacred Records; for more plain and poſitive proof we have not for the belief of any Article of the Chriſtian Faith. The Evidence I here offer you is Chriſt's own Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who without ſcruple tells us, they belong to the Kingdom of Heaven; Mat. 19.14. <hi>Suffer them,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>to come unto me;</hi> they are the undoubted Heirs of it, they have an unqueſtionable Right to it; by the Grace of God theirs it is, and into it they enter when they die. If we will not believe Chriſt, who ſhall we believe? Take away the credit of his Evidence, and what ſhall we receive for Truth? Had we no other Teſtimony in all God's Book aſſerting the bleſſedneſs of dying Infants, this is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to reſolve all Doubts about it, they being ſuch, as is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent from what hath been ſaid, to whom the Lord will not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute Sin. I once more ſay, to their Eternal Condemnation.</p>
            <p>And if ſo, to conclude, I account it highly unreaſonable, that Man ſhould attribute the Salvation of dying Infants to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or thing ſhort of the Grace of God in Chriſt Jeſus, upon which Foundation alone the Salvation and Bleſſedneſs of dying Infants ſtandeth, and that moſt fure. Moſt unworthy therefore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45045:16"/>of God and Chriſt do they ſpeak, who talk of a Foederal Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, making the Faith and Holineſs of Parents the Baſis on which they build the Bleſſedneſs of their Infants. What is this leſs, than to ſet themſelves up for Saviours, or at leaſt to make themſelves Partners with Chriſt in the Work of Salvation? Is not this apparently to charge the Grace of God as deficient to ſave dying Infants, without the Faith and Piety of Parents concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring? At this rate of arguing, what muſt become of thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren who have not the advantage of the Faith and Holineſs of Parents, who may either be taken away by Death, leaving their little ones behind them; or elſe if they live, they may be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly void and deſtitute of Saving-faith, and manifeſt Slaves to Sin and the Devil, as too many in this profeſſing Nation are? And in either of theſe caſes, which be very common, what muſt become of their poor dying Infants, if the Grace of God in Chriſt be not ſufficient to ſave them without the Holineſs of Parents? But as this Pretence reflects unworthily on God, ſo it is very falſe in it ſelf, as we could ſhew were that our buſineſs: We confeſs, that the Children of Believers have a great advantage of others, in point of a pious Education, but not one jot in point of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their Infants dying before they come to reap the advantage of ſuch Education; to ſay otherwiſe, is to aſſert that which is not many degrees ſhort of Blaſphemy. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly, If dying Infants are bleſſed upon God's not imput<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sin unto them, then how vain and fruitleſs is that pretence and practice of Baptizing Infants, as they call it, in order to their making them Members of the Church, Children of God, and Heirs or Inheritors of the Kingdom of Heaven? But if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be baptized they are in truth the Children of God, what doth their Baptiſm avail them? are they afterwards any more the Heirs of God's Kingdom than they were before? Or can it be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally ſuppoſed, that God hath left it to the liberty, choice, and within the power of a Prieſt to ſave or damn Souls, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, or refuſing, upon every Summons given him on the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a languiſhing and dying Infant, to come and baptize it? O no, their Salvation is ſecured upon a better Bottom; altho the generality believe, that if their Infants die before they be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45045:16"/>or ſprinkled, they be not much, if one whit better than Beaſts in their death, nor muſt by any means have a Chriſtian Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, with our Parſon's Vote, but be caſt into a Hole behind the Church, or ſome other place where they bury the Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, Self-murderers, and the like, without the uſual Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties appointed for the burial of the dead: and therefore when a weak Child is midwif'd into the World, what running and ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is to call the Parſon, as if a few drops of Water out of his hand were enough to quench the Flames of Hell. This well conſidered, muſt be judg'd highly ridiculous in the Sentiment of every wiſe Man; ten thouſand pities it is, that God's Ordinance is ſo changed, that poor people are ſo amuſed; and that our Learned and pious Doctors of the Church do not rectify this prevaling Miſtake the People are under, by their ſincere and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout labours to reſtore Sacred Baptiſm to its Primitive Purity; at whoſe door it lies, that their Prieſts in adminiſtring of that Ordinance, may in point of practice as apparently agree with that of the Apoſtles, as 'tis evident they deſire to be accounted their Succeſſors. But,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, and to conclude, If dying Infants are bleſſed upon God's not imputing Sin unto them, then here is comfort to ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful Mothers who have been long afflicted, refuſing, with <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel,</hi> to be comforted for their Children: If this will not relieve you under your Diſtreſſes, what will? Here's enough to remove all your Fears, and to ſatisfy your Minds with reference to the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal State of your deceaſed Babes. Let this ſtop the Springs that have been opened, and wipe away all thoſe trickling Tears which have been as ſo many Evidences of your compaſſion and paſſionate concern to and for your beloved, tho deceaſed Infants. Fear not, dear Souls, God who hath a better right to them than you had, has more tender compaſſion of them than you can have: If you have (<hi>who are evil,</hi> Mat. 7.9, 10, 11.) ſo much goodneſs as to wiſh them Heaven, God is much more good, and will give them Heaven. Therefore give no longer way to needleſs ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſity and fear on their account, whoſe happineſs renders them capable of exhorting you to ſpend your Cares, Fears, and Tears, on ſome other Subject, ſaying, as Chriſt to the Daughters of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:45045:17"/>Luke 23.28. <hi>Weep not for me, but weep for your ſelves and your Children,</hi> that is, your ſinful and miſerable Poſterity nay, rather rejoice and comfort your ſelves, for 'tis better with us than you have imagined, being ſuch unto whom the Lord imputes no Sin. Nothing remains now, but that we who ſurvive our deceaſed Babes, do give all diligence in the practice of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, whereunto we are called, <hi>to make our own Calling and Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.10, 11. <hi>that ſo an abundant entrance may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us into Glory,</hi> there to rejoice, not only in our own Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but in a more certain aſſurance of our Childrens alſo, if ſuch a thing can be, ſince our Apoſtle ſo expreſly ſays, <hi>Bleſſed is the Man unto whom the Lord will not impute Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
